A Guide to the Randolph-De Potestad Family Papers, 1826-1913
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Randolph-De Potestad Papers, 1826-1913.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 93.1
33 items.
Randolph Family.; De Potestad Family.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1993.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Randolph sisters were members of the Tuckahoe branch of the Randolph family, and the De Potestads are related by marriage to the Randolph sisters. Biographical information relating to the Randolph and de Potestad families can be found in Southern Women and Their Families in the 19th Century: Papers and Diaries. Series A, Holding of the Southern Historical Collection, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill. Part 6: Virginia Collections.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence between Mary G. Randolph and her sister Margaret H. Randolph, as well as personal letters and papers of Robert and Alice de Potestad. Included with the de Potestad materials are a poultry breeding catalog, a check, and two obituaries. The Randolph correspondence contains a poem entitled "All the World's in Paris." The bulk of the undated material relates to the Randolph sisters.
The Randolph materials relate to family matters and social events taking place at Tuckahoe Plantation (Goochland County), Prospect Hill, Richmond, and Williamsburg, Virginia. Some events alluded to include: various social gatherings and discussion regarding those attending, family illnesses, and the sale of Tuckahoe Plantation. Some of the personalities discussed include: Vice President Calhoun, Ella Wickham, Mrs. Ambler, William Lightfoot, The Honorable Mr. Madison, Mr. Peyton, Judge Brockenbrough, the Robinsons, Mrs. Cabell, Louisa Patterson, Mrs. Fitzhugh, The Ritchies, Mr. Galt, Mary Taylor, Mr. Harrison and family members Louisa, Harriet, Aunt Eliza, Uncle (Charles) Wingfield, "Billy" and Margarets's mother.
The de Potestad correspondence between Robert and Alice discusses family matters, events at "Dalton" (Ellicot City, Maryland), descriptions of a business trip to Madrid and Lisbon by Robert, and the birth of a daughter to Alice's father. Some names mentioned in the letters and other materials include: Mildred, Marques de Guell (Spanish Charg頤'Affaires), King of Spain, Sevillard, Lopez Roberts, Charlie Dorsey, Madame La Douairiere, Alexandre della Faille de Leverghem (Marie-Jeanne-Adolphine-Mols), Comtesse Douairiere de Turck de Kersbeek (Valerie Lothaire Catherine Marie Joseph della Faille de Leverghem), Samuel Kno (?) George, and Edith Van de Ware.
Arrangement
Chronologically arranged. Undated materials are placed at the end.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Randolph family.; De Potestad family.
Persons:
Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850.; De Potestad, Alice L.G.; De Potestad, Robert.; Randolph, Margaret H.; Randolph, Mary G.
Subjects:
Plantation life-- Maryland.; Plantation life-- Virginia.
Corporate Names:
Dalton Plantation (Md.); Tuckahoe Plantation (Goochland County, Va.)
Geographical Names:
Maryland--Social life and customs--20th century.; Richmond (Va.)--Social life and customs--19th century.; Virginia--Social life and customs-- 19th century.; Williamsburg (Va.)- -Social life and customs--19th century.
Contents List
- Mary Randolplh, Richmond, to sister [Margaret Randolph], 4 November 1826. (Folder 1)
  Concerns family matters.
- Mary [Randolph], Richmond, to father, Richmond, 28 February 1828. (Folder 1)
  Concerns family matters and social events. Pencil note idicates Mary Randolph married Dr. Chapman -Philadelphia.
- Mary [Randolph], Philadelphia, to Margaret [Randolph], Tuckahoe, 2 November 1828. (Folder 1)
  Concerns family matters and social events. Letter contains one page written to Harriet and Henry.
- Mary [Randolph], Richmond, to Margaret H. Randolph, Williamsburg, 6 November 1829. (Folder 1)
  Concerns family matters and social events.
- Mary [Randolph], Richmond, to "Pig" [Margaret Randolph], 16 November 1829. (Folder 1)
- Mary [Randolph], Richmond, to Margaret H. Randolph, Williamsburg, 26 November 1829. (Folder 1)
  Concerns family matters and social events. Vice President Calhoun mentioned as attending dinner at Mrs. Randolph's.
- [Mary Randolph?], Richmond, to "Pig" [Margaret Randolph], 8 December 1829. (Folder 1)
  Concerns family matters and friends.
- Mary [Randolph], Philadelphia, to Margaret H. Randolph, Richmond, 17 November 1830. (Folder 1)
- [Alice?], Paris, to Robert de Potestad, "Dalton", Ellicott City, Md. (Folder 2)
  Concerns family matters. In French.
- Poultry catalog, 1906. (Folder 2)
  Catalog of faverolles, lakenvelders and other newly imported breeds. Catalog from Dr. A. H. Phelps, Glen Falls, N. Y. - a breeder.
- [Robert de Potestad], Lisbon, to Alice [de Potestad], 12 August 1908. (Folder 2)
  Concerns a trip and family matters.
- [Robert de Potestad], Lisbon, to [Alice de Potestad], 20 August 1908. (Folder 2)
  Gives the details of a trip to Lisbon.
- Check to Charlie Dorsey from Alice L. G. de Potestad, 2 July 1910. (Folder 2)
  The amount was $9.60 through the Patapsco National Bank of Ellicott City. Back has Charlie Dorsey's sign (x) and is witnessed by M. J. Martin.
- Obituary, 3 September 1911. (Folder 2)
  Obituary of Madame la Comtesse Douairiere Alexandre della Faille de Leverghem, nee Marie Jeanne Adolphine Mols. In French.
- Obituary, 27 November 1912. (Folder 2)
  Obituary of La Comtesse Douairiere de Turck de Kersbeek, nee Valerie Lothaire Catherine Marie Joseph della Faille de Leverghem. In French.
- Envelope. Addressed to Samuel Kno (?) George Esquire, "Dalton," Ellicott City, Howard County, Md., 13 December 1912. (Folder 2)
- Edith Van de Ware to Alice [de Potestad], 15 August 1913. (Folder 2)
- [Mary Randolph], Richmond, to Margaret H. Randolph, Williamsburg, 28 January. (Folder 3)
  Concerns family matters. Social events and the disposal of Tuckahoe.
- M. W. Randolph, Richmond, to Mademoiselle M. Randolph, Tuckahoe, 1 June. (Folder 3)
- Mildred, Madrid, to Robbie [Robert de Potestad?], 23 June. (Folder 3)
- MGR [Mary Randolph] to "Pig" [Margaret Randolph], Prospect Hill. (Folder 3)
- MGR [Mary Randolph] to "Pig" [Margaret Randolph]. (Folder 3)
- MGR [Mary Randolph] to "Pig" [Margaret Randolph]. (Folder 3)
- MGR [Mary Randolph] to Margaret H. Randolph, Prospect Hill. (Folder 3)
- MGR [Mary Randolph] to Margaret Randolph, Prospect Hill. (Folder 3)
- "Cousin Mary" to Margaret H. Randolph, Prospect Hill. (Folder 3)
  Concerns arrangements to stay with her during Mary's wedding.
- Mary [Randolph] to Margaret H. Randolph, Williamsburg. (Folder 3)
  Segment of letter with address and one sentence on reverse side.
- [Mary?] to Margaret H. Randolph, Prospect Hill. (Folder 3)
  Concerns an upcoming visit with Margaret. Some notes pencilled in.
- Envelope addressed to Margaretta H. Randolph, WIlliamsburg. (Folder 3)
- Envelope addressed to Miss Margaret Randolph, Prospect Hill. (Folder 3)
- Poem: "All the World's in Paris." (Folder 3)
- [Milly?] to Alice [de Potestad]. (Folder 3)
  Concerns family matters including the birth on Saturday of father's daughter.